Ryan Essel

Bronx, NY | (412) 498-2518 | spucti19@gmail.com

https://ryanessel-portfolio.onrender.com/about https://www.linkedin.com/in/ryan-essel-a198b9257/ https://github.com/ryanessel

Summary

As a seasoned B2B sales professional with five years of experience, I've honed my skills in relationship building and client management. Seeking a new challenge and a career change, I enrolled in Ironhack's Web Development Bootcamp to learn the skills needed to create responsive and efficient web applications. The program has provided me with a solid foundation in programming languages and frameworks, and I'm excited to leverage my sales background to build products that meet the needs of both businesses and their customers.

Technical Skills: JavaScript, Express.js, MongoDB, Node.js, HTML, CSS, ReactJs, C# .Net Framework, Responsive Design, Tailwind, Daisy IU, Hyper Terminal, Git, GitHub, Wordpress.

Projects

Dungeon Game

A simple dungeon RPG games with multiple ways of dispatching enemies.

Technologies Used: HTML, CSS, JavaScript, Git

Game Message Board

A server-side web app that is reminiscent of the website gamefaqs.com. Sign, up, make threads and post. **Technologies Used**: JavaScript, Node.JS, MongoDB, Mongoose, Express, Handlebars, OnRender

Quotes, Parts, DB System

Example of web app database that lets you add and update parts with various attributes and make quotes to customers.

Technologies Used: ReactJS, JavaScript, NodeJS, MongoDB, Express, HTML, CSS, OnRender

Portfolio Website

Professional Portfolio Website that outlines my skills and projects.

Technologies Used: ReactJS, JSX, JavaScript, NodeJS, MongoDB, Express, HTML, CSS, Tailwind, Daisy UI, OnRender

Professional Experience

Sales Representative

Feb 2018 - Present

Nishiyama Corporation of America

Great Neck, NY

- Successfully manage customer inquiries, issue quotes, RFQ, and POs, consistently meeting or exceeding sales targets.
- Maximize profitability for each PO by identifying opportunities for upselling and cross-selling.
- Utilize CSS and JS to add extra functionality to Kintone form platform, including developing an algorithm
 that exports PO table data to Excel CSV in a readable format, complete with formulas for calculated
 cells.

Translator/Interpreter (Japanese/English)

Sept 2015 - Feb 2018

Bucyrus Precision Tech

Bucyrus, OH

- Provide accurate technical document translations between Japanese/English and English/Japanese, ensuring clear communication and understanding between all parties.

Education

Ironhack - Miami, FL(Remote)

Jun 2022 - Dec 2022

Full Stack Web Development (400+hours)

May 2009 - May 2014

Duquesne University - Pittsburgh, PA International Relations BS